Guide to the Debate Team Records, 1903 - 1981 (bulk 1948-1976)
Duke University. University Archives
Debate Team records 1903-1981, bulk 1948-1976
Duke University. University Archives
2 linear feet
The Duke University Debate Team was formed around 1897 at Trinity College (now Duke University). The Debate Team records include a constitution, minutes, correspondence, season summaries, debate topic announcements, debate match announcements, fliers, member lists, petition to join Tau Kappa Alpha (now Delta Sigma Rho-Tau Kappa Alpha), a research paper, certificates, photographs, memorabilia, newsletters, clippings, and scrapbooks. Major subjects include Trinity College history, Duke University students, political activity, student groups, debate, opinions about the Cold War, freedom of speech, the Speech Association of American (now the Speech Communication Association), the 1954-1955 Debate Team conflict, and Delta Sigma Rho-Tau Kappa Alpha. Materials range in date from 1903 to 1981 (bulk 1948-1976). English.
UA.31.12.0003
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
Gift; 1976-1982.
Historical Note
The Duke University Debate Team was formed around 1897 at Trinity College (now Duke University). The team hosted many tournaments against regional colleges and universities, and traveled to compete in regional and national events. English Professor Joseph C. Wetherby was the longtime coach of the team, from about 1947 until 1976. Wetherby was also an officer in the Speech Association of America (now the Speech Communication Association). Under Professor Wetherby's direction, the Duke University Debate Team won state, regional, and national honors.
In 1954, the Speech Association of America announced a national topic that would test Duke University's tradition of academic freedom: "Resolved: That the United States should extend diplomatic recognition to the Communist government of China." In preparation for competition, Edwin Chapman, Jr., a Duke University freshman from Newport News, Va., wrote his congressman, Representative Edward J. Robeson, Jr., requesting information on the topic. Robeson promptly replied, expressing amazement "that such a topic ... was even seriously considered by any group of persons who are normally intelligent and responsibly informed." He advised Chapman not to debate the positive position "as quotations from your statements may embarrass you for the rest of your life." Additionally, the congressman requested the names of the Debate Club faculty advisor at Duke and the members of the National Debating Council.
Shortly following that correspondence, Professor Wetherby warned his fellow coaches of possible trouble with the debate topic in the regional newsletter of Tau Kappa Alpha, the national forensic honor society. Before long, the Associated Press had reported the Duke incident along with a growing nationwide controversy. The biggest story concerned President Eisenhower being questioned about directives from the Secretaries of the Army and Navy forbidding the teams at West Point and Annapolis from debating the topic.
In support of uncensored discussion, Professor Wetherby appeared on a See It Now television show with Wayne C. Eubank of the University of New Mexico, President of Tau Kappa Alpha. Immediately after the program, Wetherby began receiving mostly favorable letters and telegrams from throughout the country. The president of Duke University, A. Hollis Edens, understood the significance of the issue, and did not interfere with either the student group or its faculty advisor. The Speech Association of American ultimately retained the debate topic and students participated in the national competition with no major conflicts.
Other events in team history during the 1960s include a May 1960 appearance on the nationally-televised College Bowl. A subset of the Debate Team competed on the show, winning against Antioch College and Michigan State University. In 1964, two Duke University Debate Team members went to the Federal Penitentiary in Atlanta, Ga. to debate with prisoners on the topics of "Resolved: that the federal government should guarantee an opportunity for higher education to all qualified high school graduates." In 1966, the team won the national collegiate championship, after sixteen rounds of debates against Butler University and Vanderbilt University. Duke University also had an all-women debate team for a brief time.
The Duke University chapter of Delta Sigma Rho-Tau Kappa Alpha, the intercollegiate forensics honor society, was established around 1916. The honor society is devoted to the ideals of public speaking and forensics excellence. Membership in the honor society allows Duke University to participate in elite competitions.
As of 2003, the Debate Team (now Duke Debate) is active at Duke University.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the Duke University Debate Team, founded around 1897 at Trinity College (now Duke University). Includes extensive coverage and correspondence relating to the 1954-1955 Debate Team Controversy on the topic of the United States extending diplomatic recognition to the People's Republic of China. Scrapbooks include photographs, clippings, correspondence, and memorabilia. Materials range in date from 1903 to 1981 (bulk 1948-1976).
Subject Headings
Cold War -- Public opinion; Debates and debating -- United States; Delta Sigma Rho --Tau Kappa Alpha -- History; Duke University. Debate Team; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Forensics (Public speaking) -- Societies, etc.; Freedom of speech -- United States; Speech Communication Association; Tau Kappa Alpha -- History
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Constitution and bylaws, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Season summaries and annual reports, 1948-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Results and scores, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, general, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, general, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, with alumni, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, with alumni, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Debate topics, 1953-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Debate Team Controversy, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Petition to Tau Kappa Alpha, ca. 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tau Kappa Alpha, Duke chapter records, 1948-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Member lists, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Certificates, ca. 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Match announcements, 1903-1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General publicity, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, ca. 1957, ca. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tournament Ribbon, "Fifteenth Annual NDT," ca. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Duke Debate Team newsletter, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1927, 1948-1950, 1961-1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Debate Team Controversy, research paper by student Elizabeth Molsen, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook, 1947-1962 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
Related Material
Joseph C. Wetherby papers.
University Archives, Duke University.
Speaker and Gavel [serial publication of Tau Kappa Alpha].
Periodicals, Duke University.